so now let's talk about how big the
twole page table gets say we have a
32-bit address space and a 4 kiloby Page
let's say we're using a 1024 entry outer
page table and 1,24 entry inner tables
there can be many of them up to 10,24 of
them and let's say that a page table
entry is 8 bytes assuming that our page
table entry is 8 bytes and that we have
a program that uses virtual memory at
the beginning of memory from addresses
zero through this and at the top of the
memory from address this to the end
let's look at what the flat page table
size will be and what our two level page
table size will be with this split
between the inner and outer page tables
the flat page table size will have one
entry for each possible page so we have
2 to the 32nd Pages 2 to the 12 bytes in
each page so we have 2 to the 20th
entries and the total size will be 8 *
this which ends up being 8 megabytes for
the two- level page table we need to
figure out how many inner page tables do
we have here and here our address is now
composed of a 12bit offset to index into
the 4 kilobyte page a 10 bit outer page
number and the 10 bit inner page number
they need to add up to 3 two which they
do so we know that we need to have the
outer page table and its size will be 2
to the 10th entries times 8 bytes per
entry here which ends up being 8
kilobytes for the outer page table now
the question is which of these entries
need to point to actual inner page
tables and which ones can simply say
that there is no inner page table to
figure that out we need to see which of
the inner page table entries do we need
to actually point to pages of memory and
which ones can simply be empty thus we
will decompose these addresses this part
of the address is the page offset the
upper part is the page number and we
need to split this 20 bit page number
into 10bit groups so let's just write it
out we have 0 0 0 0 these are the two
zeros another hex digit for Z
the one and the zero this is the outer
page number this is the inner page
number as you can see all of the
addresses in this range have the same
outer page number we start at zero we
end at zero so only the entry number
zero here needs to point to an actual
inner page table for this address range
the page number goes from
F0 to fffff F these page number numbers
also have the same outer page number
it's all ones so only the last outer
page table entry needs to point to an
actual inner page table note that there
are 1,24 entries here only two of which
point to Inner page tables so there is
1,22 entries that simply say nothing so
we have two inner page table times
what's the size of one of them well the
size is 1,24 entries times 8 bytes per
entry which gives us a total of 16
kilobytes adding the size of the outer
page table we get only 24 kiloby so the
size of a twole page table for this
application is only 24 kiloby compared
to 8 megabytes for the flat page table
and this is why multi-level page tables
are almost exclusively used in today's
processors especially when we have a
64-bit address space because for a 64
address space the flat page table size
would be too large to fit in memory but
a multi-level table will fit mostly
because the outermost page table will
have many empty entries so we will need
very few of these inner page tables